Guide to the Frederic Collin Walcott Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederic Collin Walcott papers
1850-1948
MS 529
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.5
(19 boxes, 1 folio)
The early papers relate to Walcott's business concerns and his game preserve. The bulk of the collection covers the period from 1915-1919 when Walcott was with the Rockefeller Foundation War Relief Commission and the U.S. Food Administration. Beginning with 1929 there is some correspondence from his career as Republican Senator from Connecticut. The remainder of the collection relates to Walcott's work in Polish relief (1939-1940) and his interest in conservation. Other persons represented include William Henry Welch (1850-1934); Herbert Hoover, with whom Walcott worked regarding Belgian relief, the Food Administration, and later as Senator; William Howard Taft; and many leaders of the American business community.
Walcott, Frederic Collin, 1869-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William W. Walcott, 1961.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts and printed material concerning Frederic Collin Walcott, manufacturer, banker, and U.S. Senator. The main body of the correspondence commences with 1910 and relates to Walcott's business concerns and his game preserve. The bulk of the collection covers the period 1915 to 1919 and may be divided into two periods: 1915 to 1917 (with his work for the Rockefeller Foundation War Relief Commission) and 1917 to 1919 (with his work for the United States Food Administration). From 1920 to 1928 there is little material. Beginning with 1929, there is some correspondence from his career as a Republican Senator from Connecticut, 1925-1935. The remainder of the collection relates to Walcott' s work in Polish Relief, 1939-1940, and his continued interest in conservation.
Notable persons in the collection are William Henry Welch, Walcott's uncle and an eminent pathologist, and Herbert Clark Hoover, with whom Walcott worked in Belgian Relief, the Food Administration, and later as Senator. There are also several letters from William Howard Taft, an autograph of Woodrow Wilson, and correspondence with many of the leaders of the American business community.
Biographical / Historical
Frederic C. Walcott: investment banker and manufacturer, 1907-1915; officer and director of various corporations until 1922; engaged in Polish and Belgian relief work, 1915-1917; U.S. Food Administration worker, 1917-1919; member of Connecticut State Senate, 1925, 1927; active on state commissions, 1923-1928; U.S. Senator from Connecticut, 1929-1935; welfare commissioner of Connecticut, 1935-1939; trustee of numerous colleges and institutions.
List of Principal Correspondents in the Walcott Collection
Allen, Henry Justin (1868-1950) Arnold, Joseph Addison, (b. 1876) Ballard, Samuel Thruston (1855-1926) Baylis, Charles Thomas (b. 1869) Beebe, William (b. 1877) Brandegee, Frank Bosworth (1864-1924) Burnham, John Bird (1869-1939) Capper, Arthur (1865-1951) Carlton, Newcomb (1869-1953) Coffin, Charles Albert (1844-1926) Deneen, Charles Samuel (1863-1940) Draper, William Kinnicutt (1863-1926) Dulles, Allen Welsh (b. 1893) Dunn, Gano (b. 1870) Embree, Edwin Rogers (b. 1883) Farnam, Henry Walcott (1853-1933) Fess, Simeon Davison (1861-1936) Fisher, Irving (1867-1947) Garfield, Harry Augustus (1863-1942) Glenn, Otis Ferguson (1879-1959) Goff, Guy Despard (1866-1933) Goldsborough, Phillips Lee (1865-1946) Good, James William (1866-1929) Grant, Madison (1865-1937) Grant, William West (1846-1934) Greene, Jerome Davis (1874-1959) Greene, Warwick (1879-1929) Greenway, James Cowan (b. 1877) Grew, Joseph Clark (b. 1880) Hadley, Arthur Twining (1856-1930) Hammond, John Hays (1855-1936) Hastings, Daniel Oren (b. 1874) Hemphill, Alexander Julian (1856-1920) Herrick, Myron Timothy (1854-1929) Hilles, Charles Dewey (1867-1949) Honnold, William Lincoln (1866-1950) Hoover, Herbert Clark (b. 1874) Howland, Charles P. (1869-1932) James, Henry (1879-1947) Kahn, Otto Hermann (1867-1934) Kean, Hamilton Fish (1862-1941) Kellogg, Frederic S. Lamont, Thomas William (1870-1948) Low, Seth (1850-1916) Mac Arthur, Douglas (b. 1880) McCann, George (1864-1932) McCormick, Vance Criswell (1872-1946) McCulloch, Roscoe Conkling (1880-1955) McCumber, Porter James (1858-1933) McLean, George Payne (1857-1932) Metcalf, Jesse Houghton (1860-1942) Mott, John Raleigh (1865-1955) Mott, Thomas Bentley (1865-1952) Newton, Walter Hughes (1880-1941) Osborne, Henry Zenas (1848-1923) Page, Walter Hines (1855-1918) Patterson, Robert Urie (1877-1950) Patterson, Roscoe Conkling (1876-1954) Pierson, Lewis Eugene (b. 1870) Pinchot, Gifford (1865-1946) Richey, Lawrence (1885-1959) Ritchie, Albert Cabell (1876-1936) Rockefeller, John Davidson (1839-1937) Rockefeller, John Davidson (b. 1874) Rose, Wickliffe (1862-1931) Sherman, James Schoolcraft (1855-1912) Stimson, Henry Lewis (1867-1950) Stokes, Anson Phelps (1874-1958) Strong, Benjamin (1872-1928) Taft, William Howard (1857-1930) Thomas, John (1874-1945) Townsend, John Gillis (b. 1871) Tumulty, Joseph Patrick (1879-1954) Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick (1884-1951) Van Hise, Charles Richard (1857-1918) Wadsworth, Eliot (1876-1959) Walcott, Frederic Collin (1869-1949) Warburg, Felix M. (1871-1937) Welch, William Henry (1850-1934) Whitney, Caspar (1864-1929) Wickersham, George Woodward (1858-1936) Wilber, David Forrest (1859-1928) Wilson, Woodrow (1856-1924) Addenda: Eliot, Charles William (1834-1926) Gary, Elbert Henry (d. 1927) Graves, Henry Solon (1871-1951) McAdoo, William Gibbs (1863-1941) Paderewski, Ignace Jan (1860-1941) Page, Thomas Nelson (1853-1922) Root, Elihu (1845-1937) Sedgwick, Ellery (b. 1872) Washington, Booker Taliaferro (1859-1915)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
United States -- Politics and government; Banks and banking -- United States; Business; Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Game reserves -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Food supply; World War, 1914-1918 -- Poland; World War, 1939-1945; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Diaries; Businessmen; Conservationists; Legislators; Politicians; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969; Farnam, Henry W. (Henry Walcott), 1853-1933; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Kahn, Otto H., 1867-1934; McAdoo, W. G. (William Gibbs), 1863-1941; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1839-1937; Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison), 1874-1960; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Walcott, Frederic Collin, 1869-1949; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Knickerbocker Bank & Trust Company; United States Food Administration
- Inventory, 1850-1948
  - Correspondence
    - 1876, 1892, 1906-1912 August (Box 1)
    - 1912 September-1914 (Box 2)
    - 1915-1916 February (Box 3)
    - 1916 March-1917 February (Box 4)
    - 1917 March-December (Box 5)
    - 1918 January-September (Box 6)
    - 1918 October-1927 (Box 7)
    - 1928-1934 May 1 (Box 8)
    - 1934 May 2-1939 (Box 9)
    - 1940-1948, undated (Box 10)
  - Diaries and album
    - Diary and notebook of trip to England, France, Italy, and Belgium, with sketches and with miscellaneous papers laid in, 1915-1916 (Box 11)
    - Diary, with miscellaneous papers laid in, 1917-1918 (Box 11)
    - Notebook on European rations, 1918 (Box 11)
    - Photograph album "to accompany the report of my cruise along the Gulf Coast... in quest of information regarding the Brown Pelicans for the United States Food Administration. T. Gilbert Pearson", 1918 (Box 11)
    - Diary of European tour, with miscellaneous papers laid in, 1939 (Box 11)
  - World War I
    - United States Food Administration and the Rockefeller Foundation: printed and near-print material (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous publications, mainly re food (Box 13)
    - Translation of German writing on postwar economic conditions (Box 13)
    - Publications and miscellaneous papers (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous papers re non-World War I activities, 1850-1947, undated (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks (descriptions are not exhaustive)
    - Poland, World War I (Box 15)
    - Poland, World War I (Box 16)
    - Knickerbocker Bank & Trust Company, 1908-1911 (Box 17)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 17)
    - 1928-1931 (Box 18)
  - Clippings (descriptions are not exhaustive)
    - Poland (Box 19)
    - Hoover (Box 19)
    - Germany (Box 19)
  - Oversize
    - United States Food Administration: posters, charts (Box 20)
    - Photographs: Wilson, Hoover, Myron T. Herrick, Hoover Cabinet, F. C. Walcott (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook: memorabilia of Army-Navy "E" flag presentation to Remington Bridgeport Works, 1942 (Box 20)